ARPIT AGARWAL

+31 627241677 (M) arpiagar88@gmail.com

Summary

Senior Engineer and Team Leader with over 10 year of experience in comprehensive design and development of the backend infrastructure for web services, distributed systems and software applications, with a proven track record of leading people to achieve success by setting up high performing teams. Domain experience in developing core business services in a mirco-services ecosystem, practices ensuring reliability of production services and scaling infrastructure.

Languages, Technologies & Paradigms

- Java, Python, Perl, Node.js, Ruby, JavaScript
- Apache Kafka, Storm
- SOA/Microservices
- Ansible, Puppet

Skills

- People Management
- Agile practices
- Coaching/Mentoring

- Dropwizard, J2EE, Guice, Django, Flask, Pandas
- API Design
- Chaos Engineering
- Bare Metal/ Kubernetes
- Effective communication
- Technical Leadership

- MySQL, Cassandra, Redis, Hbase, Hadoop
- Distributed systems
- CI/CD, Gitlab, Jenkins
- Performance management
- Commercial awareness

Employment Experience

Senior Engineer & Team Leader	Booking.com (Amsterdam)	Sep 2016 - Present

- Leading the team responsible for the Booking.com website and mobile app high availability and reliability on production.
- Responsible for People and Performance management for a team of 6 team members.
- Leading the Chaos Engineering efforts at Booking.com. Building Chaos Orchestrator Java framework to enable Chaos experimentation across various Booking.com systems.
- Worked on Reliability Collaboration Model resulting into clear expectations with Reliability and product teams over ownership of the service.
- Working on tooling to increase Reliability of systems and reducing operational toil for SREs.
- Implementing SLI/SLOs for different systems that the team owns.
- Maintained and scaled the Push Notification infrastructure at Booking.com for campaigns.

Senior Sc	oftware	Devel	oper
-----------	---------	-------	------

Flipkart Internet Pvt Ltd (Bangalore)

Sep 2014 - Aug 2016

- Re-architected and redesigned one of core business services Order Management Service(OMS) at Flipkart.
- Re-designed the service using HBase and multimaster VoltDB to scale linearly.
- Implemented Order Search service on order metadata pivots using ElasticSearch in the new JAVA service.
- Written a wrapper service so that the client could be supported on data model and API contracts for existing service unless they switch to new service
- Flipkart was moving to Cloud for better infrastructure management. Worked over the migration of OMS service and DB to the new infrastructure/cloud.
- Designed and then written the data ingestion infrastructure for the new service.

 Designed and implemented a dashboard enabling various tech teams to simultaneously perform multiple operations like queue search, cluster search, queue creation, message unsideline, message count views etc.

Senior Software Engineer Paytm(Delhi) Mar 2014 – Aug 2014

- Designed and implemented the ACL (Access Control logs) API and framework providing custom permissions to various kinds of users.
- Working over the creation of a self-sustaining ecosystem fulfilling orders of various merchants
- Designing the inventory sync workflow for the merchants exposing their product status API.
- Integration of the market orders module with Google Analytics to understand the behavior of the users.
- Worked over Google Markup's for better tracking of the orders.
- Worked over the recharge module for lowend devices and fixed number of issues

Software Engineer Adobe Systems Inc (Delhi) Jun 2010 – Mar 2014

Worked on build and release tooling which involved several Python and Java based in-house frameworks.

Part-time Projects

github.com/arpiagar

- Developed a configuration parser with memcache and minimize the load time for the config file.
- Designed a load balancer algorithm using Robin Round allocation of tasks to Worker Threads.
- Designed and implemented a Django task manager enabling the user to track its daily tasks.
- Implemented an API to track number of requests coming from a particular IP and blacklist when exceeds a threshold.
- Worked over Facebook and LinkedIn API and developed a means to graphically represent the 1st degree connections data.

Education

- **B.Tech in Computer Science.**(U.P Technical University Lucknow, JSS Academy of Technical Education,)(2006-2010) 78.6%
- **C.B.S.E** (10+2) (L.N Public School) (2006) 81.2%.
- **C.B.S.E** (Lions English School) (2004) 90%.

Additional Project Achievements

Adobe Kickstart Initiative : Clipgaze Project

- Designed an Interactive Video Ecosystem ClipGaze, which provides an unparalleled viewing experience by intelligently analyzing and extracting interesting and desirable information from video on demand.
- Sponsored by Adobe Kickstart Innovation Team with \$1000 to support the idea
- Received a whooping response consisting of 4000+ likes on Facebook, 200+ email sign-ups in less than two
 months.

Video Indexing Solution - Adobe Connect Feature

 Proposed and implemented a new indexing solution to index the Adobe Connect videos on the basis of their content extracted and analyzed intelligently by using the techniques of OCR(Optical Character Recognition), Video Analytics and NLP (Natural Language Processing).